<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
    <control> <!-- Administrative metadata -->
        <recordId>NAF-0000000A</recordId> <!-- placeholder as this will be assigned within the CW -->
        <maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus> <!-- Updated when edited. May contain: "cancelled" or "deleted" or "deletedReplaced" or "deletedSplit" or "derived" or "new" or "revised" -->
        <publicationStatus>inProcess</publicationStatus> <!-- May contain: "inProcess" or "approved" -->
        <maintenanceAgency>
            <agencyName>King's Digital Laboratory</agencyName>
        </maintenanceAgency>
        <languageDeclaration> <!-- Of the EAC-CPF file. The EAC-CPF files created for the GPP project are all (at this time) in English and use the latin script. -->
            <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
            <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
        </languageDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration> <!-- Date and time format convention. -->
            <abbreviation>ISO8601</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/iso-8601-date-and-time-format.html" xlink:type="simple">Date and time format - ISO 8601</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Dates and times are formatted according to the ISO 8601 standard in the following forms: YYYY-MM-DD or YYYY-MM-DDTHH:MM:SSZ.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration> <!-- Personal and organisational naming conventions -->
            <abbreviation>NCA</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://anws.llgc.org.uk/ncarules/title.htm" xlink:type="simple">National Council on Archives Rules for the construction of personal, place and
                corporate names, 1997.</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Personal and organisational names are formatted according to NCA Rules.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration> <!-- Geographical naming conventions -->
            <abbreviation>GeoNames</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://www.geonames.org/" xlink:type="simple">GeoNames</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Geographic names are formatted according to GeoNames usage.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration>
            <abbreviation>Wikidata</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Main_Page" xlink:type="simple">Wikidata</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Geographic names may be formatted according to Wikidata usage if not present on GeoNames.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration> <!-- Geographic coordinates convention. -->
            <abbreviation>WGS84</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Geodetic_System" xlink:type="simple">World Geodetic System 1984</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>Latitude/longitude coordinates are in the WGS84 standard. Coordinates should be taken from GeoNames where possible.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration> <!-- Function thesaurus. -->
            <abbreviation>UKAT</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://www.ukat.org.uk/" xlink:type="simple">UK Archival Thesaurus</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>UKAT terms are used to specify the function/s of an EAC-CPF entity.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <localTypeDeclaration>
            <abbreviation>Name Parts</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://anws.llgc.org.uk/ncarules/title.htm" xlink:type="simple"
                >National Council on Archives Rules for the construction of personal, place and
                corporate names, 1997.</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>The name parts (and direct order) that constitute name formation are taken from the NCA Rules.</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </localTypeDeclaration>
        <localTypeDeclaration>
            <abbreviation>Date Styles</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://www.cree.name/genuki/dates.htm" xlink:type="simple"
                >Spathaky, Mike. "Old Style and New Style Dates and the change to the Gregorian Calendar: A summary for genealogists." Last modified December 13, 2011. http://www.cree.name/genuki/dates.htm</citation>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>The time period over which the Georgian papers spans includes the change from the Old Style dating system (Julian calendar, year beginning Lady Day [25th March]) to the New Style system (Gregorian calendar, year beginning 1st January). This change was implemented in Britain and her colonies in 1752 but was implemented throughout Europe at differing times in history.</p>
                <p>For the purpose of the Georgian Papers Programme Name Authority File, in EAC-CPF all dates given with no @localType attached are implicitly New Style; only those that are Old Style will include @localType="oldStyle".</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </localTypeDeclaration>
        <localTypeDeclaration>
            <abbreviation>gender</abbreviation>
            <citation xlink:href="http://homosaurus.org/terms" xlink:type="simple">Homosaurus: International Thesaurus of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Index Terms</citation>
        </localTypeDeclaration>
        <maintenanceHistory>
            <maintenanceEvent> <!-- records each maintenance/editing event that occurs throughout the life of the file -->
                <eventType>created</eventType> <!-- May contain: "cancelled" or "created" or "deleted" or "derived" or "revised" or "updated" -->
                <eventDateTime standardDateTime="2019-12-17T10:34:00Z">10:34 am, 17 December 2019</eventDateTime> <!-- ISO 8601 date-time formatting -->
                <agentType>human</agentType> <!-- May contain: "human" or "machine" -->
                <agent xml:id="GPP-00001748">Callaghan, Samantha</agent> <!-- ID may be subject to change in the CW -->
                <eventDescription>Creation of NAF for James Barry funded by the Marc Fitch Fund (https://www.marcfitchfund.org.uk/)</eventDescription> <!-- Include a full description of the maintenance event - ie: note what was created/edited during the event -->
            </maintenanceEvent>
        </maintenanceHistory>
        <sources>
            <source xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1294046">
                <sourceEntry>Wikidata ID: Q1294046</sourceEntry>
            </source>
            <source xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Barry_(surgeon)">
                <sourceEntry>Wikipedia: James Barry (surgeon)</sourceEntry>
            </source>
            <source xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.geonames.org/2965140/cork.html">
                <sourceEntry>GeoNames ID: 2965140</sourceEntry>
            </source>
            <source xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.geonames.org/2643743/london.html">
                <sourceEntry>GeoNames ID: 2643743</sourceEntry> 
            </source>
        </sources>        
    </control>
    <multipleIdentities>
    <cpfDescription> <!-- Descriptive metadata -->
        <identity>
            <entityType>person</entityType>
            <nameEntry scriptCode="Latn" xml:lang="eng"> 
                <part localType="forename">James Miranda Steuart</part>
                <part localType="surname">Barry</part>
                <part localType="epithet">doctor</part>
                <useDates>
                    <dateRange>
                        <fromDate standardDate="1809-11">ca. November 1809</fromDate>
                        <toDate standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</toDate>
                    </dateRange>
                </useDates>
                <authorizedForm>NCA</authorizedForm>
            </nameEntry>
            <nameEntry scriptCode="Latn" xml:lang="eng" localType="directOrder"> 
                <part>Barry, James Miranda Steuart, c 1789-1865, doctor</part>
                <useDates>
                    <dateRange>
                        <fromDate standardDate="1809-11">ca. November 1809</fromDate>
                        <toDate standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</toDate>
                    </dateRange>
                </useDates>
                <authorizedForm>NCA</authorizedForm>
            </nameEntry>
        </identity>
        <description>
            <existDates> <!-- Birth and death dates, if known. -->
                <dateRange>
                    <fromDate standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</fromDate>
                    <toDate standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</toDate>
                </dateRange>
            </existDates>
            <localDescription localType="gender">
                <term vocabularySource="Homosaurus">Men</term>
            </localDescription>
            <!-- For preference we prefer to capture birth and death places. If it is considered useful, further places (and dates can be captured)such as residences and so on, time permitting. -->
            <places>
                <place>
                    <placeRole>birth</placeRole>
                    <placeEntry vocabularySource="GeoNames" latitude="51.89797" longitude="-8.47061">Cork, Ireland</placeEntry>
                    <date standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</date>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeRole>death</placeRole>
                    <placeEntry vocabularySource="GeoNames" latitude="51.50853" longitude="-0.12574">London, England</placeEntry>
                    <date standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</date>
                </place>
            </places>
            <languagesUsed>
                <languageUsed> <!-- From evidence in the GPP, if possible -->
                    <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
                    <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
                </languageUsed>
                <languageUsed>
                    <language languageCode="lat">Latin</language>
                    <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
                </languageUsed>
            </languagesUsed>
            <biogHist> 
                <abstract>James Miranda Steuart Barry (c. 1789 – 25 July 1865) was a military surgeon in the British Army, born in Cork, Ireland. Barry obtained a medical degree from the University of Edinburgh Medical School, then served first in Cape Town, South Africa and subsequently in many parts of the British Empire. Before retirement, Barry had risen to the rank of Inspector General (equivalent to Brigadier General) in charge of military hospitals, the second highest medical office in the British Army. Barry not only improved conditions for wounded soldiers, but also the conditions of the native inhabitants, and performed the first caesarean section in Africa by an Irish surgeon in which both the mother and child survived the operation.</abstract>
                <p>Although Barry's entire adult life was lived as a man, Barry was born Margaret Ann Bulkley and was known as female in childhood. Barry lived as a man in both public and private life, at least in part in order to be accepted as a university student and pursue a career as a surgeon, with Barry's birth sex only becoming known to the public and to military colleagues after death.</p>
                <p>Having assumed the identity of James Barry, he arrived in Edinburgh in November 1809 and began his studies at the Medical School as a 'literary and medical student'. Barry's short stature, unbroken voice, delicate features and smooth skin led many to suspect that Barry was a young boy not past puberty, and the University Senate initially attempted to block Barry's application for the final examinations due to this apparent youth. However, the Earl of Buchan, a friend of Dr Fryer and Barry's late namesake, persuaded the Senate to relent and Barry qualified Medicinae Doctor (MD) in 1812. Barry then moved back to London, signing up for the Autumn Course 1812/1813 as a pupil of the United Hospitals of Guy's and St Thomas', whose teachers included Henry Cline and celebrated surgeon Astley Cooper. On 2 July 1813, Barry successfully passed the examination of the Royal College of Surgeons of England.</p>
                    <p>Upon joining the army, Barry was commissioned as a Hospital Assistant in the British Army on 6 July 1813, taking up posts in Chelsea and then the Royal Military Hospital in Plymouth, achieving a promotion to Assistant Surgeon to the Forces, equivalent to lieutenant, on 7 December 1815.</p>
                    <p>Following this military training, Barry was posted to Cape Town, South Africa in 1816. Through Lord Buchan, Barry had a letter of introduction to the Governor, Lieutenant General Lord Charles Henry Somerset. Following the successful, even spectacular, treatment of Lord Charles's sick daughter, Barry was welcomed into the family, maintained a close friendship with the Governor, and became his personal physician. In 1822 Somerset appointed Barry as Colonial Medical Inspector, an extraordinary jump in expectations from Barry's low military rank which brought with it great responsibility. Over ten years of work in the Cape, Barry effected significant changes, among them improvements to sanitation and water systems, improved conditions for slaves, prisoners and the mentally ill, and provision of a sanctuary for the leper population. Barry also performed one of the first known successful Caesarean sections in which both mother and child survived; the child was christened James Barry Munnik in Barry's honour, and the name was passed down through the family, leading to Barry's name being borne by a later Prime Minister of South Africa, J. B. M. Hertzog. Barry also gained enemies by criticising local officials and their handling of medical matters, but the advantage of a close relationship with the Governor meant that the repercussions of these outspoken views were usually smoothed over.</p>
                    <p>Barry was promoted to Surgeon to the Forces on 22 November 1827. Barry's subsequent posting was to Mauritius in 1828. In 1829, Barry risked a great deal of trouble by going absent without leave to return to England and treat Somerset, who had fallen ill, and remained there until Somerset's death in 1831. Barry's subsequent posting was to Jamaica, and then the island of Saint Helena in 1836. At St Helena, one clash with a fellow army surgeon resulted in Barry being arrested and court-martialled on a charge of "conduct unbecoming of the character of an Officer and a Gentleman". Barry was found not guilty, and honourably acquitted.</p>
                    <p>In 1840 Barry was posted to the Leeward Islands and Windward Islands of the West Indies, there focusing on medicine, management and improving the conditions of the troops, and receiving a promotion to Principal Medical Officer. In 1845, Barry contracted yellow fever and left for England for sick leave in October. After being cleared for duty, Barry was posted to Malta in 1846. Here Barry was severely reprimanded for inexplicably taking a seat in the local church that was reserved for the clergy, and had to deal with the threat – and eventual actuality – of a cholera epidemic, which broke out in 1850.</p>
                    <p>The following posting was to Corfu in 1851, which brought with it a promotion to the rank of Deputy Inspector-General of Hospitals on 16 May, equivalent to lieutenant colonel. From here, Barry temporarily visited the Crimea on leave — as a request to be posted there officially had been denied — where an argument took place between Barry and Florence Nightingale at Scutari Hospital. Finally, in 1857 Barry was posted to Canada, and granted the local rank of Inspector General of Hospitals (equivalent to Brigadier General) on 25 September. In that position, Barry fought for better food, sanitation and proper medical care for prisoners and lepers, as well as soldiers and their families. This local rank was confirmed as substantive on 7 December 1858.</p>  
                    <p>Wherever Barry served across the British Empire, improvements were made to sanitary conditions and the conditions and diet of both the common soldier and other, under-represented groups. Barry was outraged by unnecessary suffering, and took a heavy-handed and sometimes tactless approach to demanding improvements for the poor and underprivileged which often incited anger from officials and military officers; on several occasions Barry was both arrested and demoted for the extremity of this behaviour. Barry held strict and unusually modern views about nutrition, being completely vegetarian and teetotal, and, while keeping most personal relationships distant, was very fond of pets, particularly a beloved poodle named Psyche.</p>
                    <p>Despite protesting the decision, Barry was forcefully retired by the army on 19 July 1859 due to ill health and old age, and was succeeded as inspector general of hospitals by David Dumbreck. After a quiet retirement in London, Barry finally died from dysentery on 25 July 1865. The identity of the woman who discovered the truth of Barry's sex is disputed, but she was probably a charwoman who also laid out the dead. The charwoman, after failing to elicit payment for her services, sought redress in another way; she visited Barry's physician, Major D. R. McKinnon, who had issued the death certificate upon which Barry was identified as male. The woman claimed that Barry's body had been biologically female and had marks suggesting Barry had at one point borne a child. When McKinnon refused to pay her, she took the story to the press, and the situation became public.</p>
                <p>Barry was buried in Kensal Green Cemetery under the name James Barry and full military rank.</p>
                <citation>Wikipedia. "James Barry (surgeon)" Accessed December 17, 2019. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Barry_(surgeon)</citation>
                <p>Biography source: Wikipedia. Licensed under CC-BY-SA.</p>
            </biogHist>         
        </description>
    </cpfDescription>
        <cpfDescription> <!-- Descriptive metadata -->
            <identity>
                <entityType>person</entityType>
                <nameEntry scriptCode="Latn" xml:lang="eng"> 
                    <part localType="forename">Margaret Ann</part>
                    <part localType="surname">Bulkley</part>
                    <useDates>
                        <dateRange>
                            <fromDate standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</fromDate>
                            <toDate standardDate="1809-11">ca. November 1809</toDate>
                        </dateRange>                        
                    </useDates>
                    <authorizedForm>NCA</authorizedForm>
                </nameEntry>
                <nameEntry scriptCode="Latn" xml:lang="eng" localType="directOrder"> 
                    <part>Bulkley, Margaret Ann, ca 1789-1865</part>
                    <useDates>
                        <dateRange>
                            <fromDate standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</fromDate>
                            <toDate standardDate="1809-11">ca. November 1809</toDate>
                        </dateRange>
                    </useDates>
                    <authorizedForm>NCA</authorizedForm>
                </nameEntry>
            </identity>
            <description>
                <existDates> <!-- Birth and death dates, if known. -->
                    <dateRange>
                        <fromDate standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</fromDate>
                        <toDate standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</toDate>
                    </dateRange>
                </existDates>
                <localDescription localType="gender">
                    <term vocabularySource="Homosaurus">Women</term>
                </localDescription>
                <!-- For preference we prefer to capture birth and death places. If it is considered useful, further places (and dates can be captured)such as residences and so on, time permitting. -->
                <places>
                    <place>
                        <placeRole>birth</placeRole>
                        <placeEntry vocabularySource="GeoNames" latitude="51.89797" longitude="-8.47061">Cork, Ireland</placeEntry>
                        <date standardDate="1789">ca. 1789</date>
                    </place>
                    <place>
                        <placeRole>death</placeRole>
                        <placeEntry vocabularySource="GeoNames" latitude="51.50853" longitude="-0.12574">London, England</placeEntry>
                        <date standardDate="1865-07-25">25 July 1865</date>
                    </place>
                </places>
                <languageUsed> <!-- From evidence in the GPP, if possible -->
                    <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
                    <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
                </languageUsed>
                <biogHist> 
                    <abstract>Margaret Ann Bulkley was born, circa 1789, in Cork, Ireland and was raised as a girl until her late teens. Margaret took on the identity of James Miranda Steuart Barry shortly before they were admitted to medical school in Edinburgh and lived as James Barry until his death in 1865.</abstract>
                    <p>In his detailed research into Barry's early life, Michael Du Preez states that Barry was born in Cork in 1789, a birth date based on Mrs Bulkley's description of her child being fifteen years old in a letter dated 14 January 1805. Various other sources give birth dates of 1792, 1795, and 1799, but these dates are almost certainly the result of Barry later lying about age on official documents to aid passing as a man.</p>
                    <p>Barry was the second child born to Jeremiah and Mary-Ann Bulkley, and was given the name Margaret Ann. Mary-Ann Bulkley was the sister of James Barry, a celebrated Irish artist and professor of painting at London's Royal Academy. Jeremiah Bulkley ran the weigh house in Merchant's Quay, Cork. However, anti-Catholic sentiment led to his dismissal from this post. This and subsequent financial mismanagement left Mary-Ann and Barry without the support of either Jeremiah Bulkley (whose debts led to him spending time in the Marshalsea prison in Dublin) or later the Bulkleys' married son John. A third child appeared in the Bulkley family and was named Juliana. Although presented as being Barry's sister, it is likely that she was Barry's daughter as a result of childhood sexual assault, as the charwoman who discovered Barry's sex, Sophia Bishop, when laying out the body stated that pregnancy stretch marks were present.</p>
                    <p>The teenage Barry was educated with the prospect of becoming a tutor, but given a lack of evidence of any work history, the Bulkleys appear to have struggled to find Barry any suitable tutoring positions. A conspiracy appears to have developed between Barry, Mary-Ann Bulkley and some of the late James Barry's influential, liberal-minded friends (General Francisco de Miranda, Dr Edward Fryer, who had become Barry's personal tutor, and Daniel Reardon, the family's solicitor) to enable the teenage Barry to enter medical school. The University of Edinburgh was chosen and Mary-Ann and Barry boarded a Leith smack on 30 November 1809. And so, Margaret Ann Bulkley became James Barry, nephew of the late James Barry RA the Irish romantic painter and remained known thus for the next 56 years. In a letter to Daniel Reardon, sent on 14 December, Barry asked for any letters addressed to Margaret Bulkley to be forwarded to Mary-Ann Bulkley (whom Barry now refers to as "my aunt"), and mentions that '...it was very usefull [sic] for Mrs. Bulkley (my aunt) to have a Gentleman to take care of her on Board Ship and to have one in a strange country...'. Although the letter was signed "James Barry", the solicitor indiscreetly wrote on the back of the envelope 'Miss Bulkley, 14 December'; this crucial piece of evidence was the one which enabled researchers to finally confirm that Margaret Bulkley and James Barry were one and the same.</p>
                    <citation>Preez, Hercules Michael du. "Dr James Barry: The Early Years Revealed." South African Journal of Medicine 98, no. 1 (January 2008):52-58. http://www.samj.org.za/index.php/samj/article/view/130/425</citation>
                    <citation>Wikipedia. "Deborah Sampson" Accessed December 13, 2019. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deborah_Sampson</citation>
                    <p>Biography source: Wikipedia. Licensed under CC-BY-SA.</p>
                </biogHist>         
            </description>
        </cpfDescription>
    </multipleIdentities>
</eac-cpf>


